<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A common vvhore vvith all these graces grac'd: shee's very honest, beautifull and chaste. Written by Iohn Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111365</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846727</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846727</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177518</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13434)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1010:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A common vvhore vvith all these graces grac'd: shee's very honest, beautifull and chaste. Written by Iohn Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Edward Allde] for Henry Gosson, and are to be sould in Pannier-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A whore.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, imprint has "Pannier-Alley"; B1r last line has "sensuality".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:1"/>
            <p>A Common Whore VVith all theſe Graces Grac'd: Shee's very honeſt, beautifull and chaſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> IOHN TAYLOR.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON: Printed for <hi>Henry Goſſon,</hi> and are to be fould in Pannier-Alley. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:2"/>
            <head>To no matter who.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Lord, Maiſter, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Gaffer, <hi>or</hi> Knaue, Lady, Miſtreſſe, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, Gammer, <hi>or</hi> Whore, Readers.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Would not haue you to take me for a Bawde or a Pander, for that I ſend a <hi>Whore</hi> amongst you; for though it be my pleaſure to call her ſo, yet you in the peruſing of her, and conuerſing with her; ſhall finde her honeſter then ſome of your Wiues or Mothers: indeede ſhee hath no great Kindred to boaſt of, for my poore braine like <hi>Ioue</hi> was the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother that begat and bare her like a new Pall as And my Pen the Midwife that firſt wrap'd her inragged verſes in ſtead of cloutes, where the Printer hath vs'd her as he would be loth to be vs'd himſelfe, for he hath publiſh'd and proclaim'd all her faults to the view of the world, and yet I know the poore <hi>Whores</hi> paine is not paſt, for now ſhe is to be examin'd a thouſand wayes, &amp; tortur'd vpon
<pb facs="tcp:177518:3"/>the Rack of cenſure, and amongst all that ſhal view and handle her, the hot whoremaiſter will deale moſt diſcourteouſly with her, for when he perceiues her honeſty too hard for his Knauery, he will in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, with three <hi>tuſhes,</hi> foure <hi>piſhes,</hi> fiue <hi>mewes,</hi> ſix wry mouthes, and ſeuen ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uruy faces, teare her and pull her worſe then the Ruſticall Rabblement did vſe to vſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon whores on former <hi>Shroue. Tueſdayes.</hi> But all's one, let him doe his worſt, ſhe is confidently arm'd with Innocencie: and the threates or danger of the bad, cannot affright her but that ſhe will attempt to recreate the good. In a word, all that is amiſſe in her, I pray you impute to my bad Tutorſhip, and her owne frailety; all that I hope of her, is, that ſhe is a merry <hi>Whore,</hi> full of good words: A kinde <hi>Whore</hi> to bee had for money or loue any where; a true <hi>Whore</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſtant, for ſhee will neuer forſake any man that will keepe her: and (by reaſon ſhee is an honeſt <hi>Whore</hi>) ſhe is a poore <hi>Whore,</hi> and hath neither money nor Sprats; ſo take my <hi>Whore</hi> amongst yon as ſhe is.</p>
            <l>Now after this, I'le be exceeding briefe</l>
            <l>To ſend another Pamphlet call'd a <hi>Thiefe;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The Hue and Cry is out, and I proteſt,</l>
            <l>Thought he ſcape hanging, yet he ſhall be preſt.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:3"/>
            <head>A WHORE.</head>
            <l>MY Booke, an honeſt <hi>Whore,</hi> I fitly call,</l>
            <l>Becauſe it treats of <hi>whores</hi> in generall:</l>
            <l>Then though this Pamphlet I doe name a <hi>whore</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Let no man ſhun her company therefore,</l>
            <l>For if ten thouſand with her lodge and lye,</l>
            <l>No reputation they ſhall loſe thereby.</l>
            <l>No coſt<note n="*" place="margin">A cheaps Whore.</note> for dyet ſhe at all requires,</l>
            <l>No charge for change of changeable Attires,</l>
            <l>No Coaches, or Carroaches ſhe doth craue,</l>
            <l>No baſe attendance of a Pand'ring Knaue,</l>
            <l>Perſumes and Paintings, ſhe abhorres and hates,</l>
            <l>Nor doth ſhe borrow haire from others pates.</l>
            <l>And this much more Ile boldly ſay for her,</l>
            <l>Who ſo redeemes her from the Stationer</l>
            <l>With whom ſhe as a Slaue is kept in hold,</l>
            <l>And at his pleaſure daily bought and ſold)</l>
            <l>I ſay, that man that doth her ranſome pay,</l>
            <l>She will requite his kindneſſe euery way,</l>
            <l>Her Inſide with ſuch Treaſurie is ſtor'd,</l>
            <l>As may become the Pocket of a Lord,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:4"/>
            <l>All, from the Cottage, to the Caſtle high,</l>
            <l>From Pallatines vnto the Peaſantry,</l>
            <l>(If ther'le permit their wiſedomes Rule their will)</l>
            <l>May keepe this <hi>Whore,</hi> and yet be honeſt ſtill.</l>
            <l>Yet is ſhe<note n="*" place="margin">A ſtrange Whore, common and yet honeſt.</note> 
               <hi>Common,</hi> vnto all that craue her,</l>
            <l>For ſixe pence honeſt man or Knaue may haucher,</l>
            <l>To be both turn'd and toſt, ſhe free affords,</l>
            <l>And (like a prating <hi>Whore</hi>) ſhe's full of words,</l>
            <l>But all her talke is to no other end,</l>
            <l>Then to teach <hi>Whoremaiſters</hi> and <hi>Whores</hi> to mend.</l>
            <l>She in plaind termes vnto the world doth tell,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Whores</hi> are the Hackneyes which men ride to hell,</l>
            <l>And by Compariſons ſhe truly makes</l>
            <l>A <hi>Whore</hi> worſe then a common Shore, or Iakes.</l>
            <l>A Succubus, a damned ſinke of ſinne,</l>
            <l>A Mire, where worſe then Swine doe wallow in,</l>
            <l>And with a <hi>Whore</hi> (although thus plaine ſhe be)</l>
            <l>She ſhewes a <hi>Whoremonger</hi> as bad as ſhe.</l>
            <l>And though I barren am of Elloquence,</l>
            <l>Nor euer vnderſtood my <hi>Accidence:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet though I haue no learning to my ſhare,</l>
            <l>A <hi>Whore</hi> to broken Lattin I'le compare;</l>
            <l>Firſt, if her minde on <hi>Whoring</hi> ſhe doth fix,</l>
            <l>She's all compact of mirth, all <hi>Meretrix,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And with ſmall teaching ſhe will ſoone decline</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mulier</hi> into the Gender Maſculine.</l>
            <l>By her Attire, of which ſex ſhe ſhould be,</l>
            <l>She ſeemes the <hi>doubtfull Gender</hi> vnto me,</l>
            <l>To either ſide her habit ſeemes to leane,</l>
            <l>And may be taken for the <hi>Epicene.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:4"/>
            <l>Vnto the <hi>Newter</hi> I compare her can,</l>
            <l>For ſhe's for thee, or me, or any man.</l>
            <l>In her Declouſions ſhe ſo farre will goe,</l>
            <l>As to the <hi>common of two, three,</hi> or moe.</l>
            <l>And come to <hi>horum harum Whorum,</hi> then</l>
            <l>She proues a great proficient amongſt men.</l>
            <l>Then after ſhe hath learn'd theſe Leſſons right,</l>
            <l>She forward goes vnto <hi>hoc leue</hi> light,</l>
            <l>She paints out <hi>pulcher,</hi> ayded by her glaſſe,</l>
            <l>She's neither <hi>bonus,</hi> or yet <hi>bonitas.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Homo</hi> for all men, is a common name,</l>
            <l>And ſhe for all men is a common ſhame.</l>
            <l>Not <hi>lapis</hi> ſingularly, her can pleaſe,</l>
            <l>She loues the plurall number <hi>lapides.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To Conſter plainely ſhe is ſeldome curlous,</l>
            <l>The two hard words of <hi>durus,</hi> and of <hi>durius,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Though ſhe's not paſt the Whip, ſhe's paſt the Rods,</l>
            <l>And knowes to ioyne her <hi>qui'es,</hi> her <hi>quea's,</hi> &amp; <hi>quods,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Actiue</hi> from the <hi>Paſſiue</hi> ſhe'le deriue,</l>
            <l>Her <hi>Mood</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mmaunds like the <hi>Imparatiue;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>She knowes no <hi>Concords,</hi> yet to all men thus,</l>
            <l>She faine would be <hi>Iucundas omnibut;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Clam</hi> is the Cloake, that couers her offence,</l>
            <l>Her goodnes all is in the <hi>Future tenſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>She's <hi>facile fieri,</hi> (quickly wonne)</l>
            <l>Or Conſt'ring truly, <hi>Eaſie to be done.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Parui ducitur probitas,</hi> ſets forth</l>
            <l>Her honeſty is rekon'd little worth.</l>
            <l>And he ſhall finde, that takes her for his choyce;</l>
            <l>An <hi>Interiection,</hi> or <hi>Imperfect voyce,</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:5"/>
            <l>Among the rules of Gender, ſhe by heart,</l>
            <l>Can without miſſing daily ſay her part.</l>
            <l>The firſt among them all ſhe liketh beſt,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Propria quae Maribus,</hi> and there ſhe'le reſt.</l>
            <l>Thus may a <hi>Whore</hi> be made (by this Conſtruction)</l>
            <l>Vnto the Grammar Rules an Introduction,</l>
            <l>But yet if Learning might be gotten ſo,</l>
            <l>Few to the Vniuerſities would goe.</l>
            <l>And all degrees, tagge ragge, and old and young,</l>
            <l>Would be well grounded in the Latine tongue:</l>
            <l>Whil'ſt many learn'd men would be forc'd to ſeeke</l>
            <l>Their liuings from the Hebrew and the Greeke.</l>
            <l>For mine owne part I dare to ſweare and vow</l>
            <l>I ne're vs'd <hi>Accidence</hi> ſo much as now,</l>
            <l>Nor all theſe Latine words here enterlac'd,</l>
            <l>I doe not know if they with ſenſe are plac'd,</l>
            <l>I in the Booke did finde them, and conclude</l>
            <l>At randon to a <hi>Whore</hi> I them allude.</l>
            <l>But leauing <hi>Latine,</hi> eu'ry Trading <hi>Wench</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Hath much more vnderſtanding of the <hi>French.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If ſhe hath learn'd great P, O Perſe O,</l>
            <l>She'le quickly know <hi>De morbo Gallico.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If in theſe Rudiments ſhe well doth enter,</l>
            <l>With any man ſhe neuer feares to venter:</l>
            <l>She's Impudently arm'd, and ſhameleſſe to,</l>
            <l>And neuer dreads what man to her can do,</l>
            <l>Her neather part to ſtake ſhe'le often lay</l>
            <l>To keepe her vpper part in faſhion, gay,</l>
            <l>She bluſhes not to haue her Trade well know<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne,</l>
            <l>Which is, ſhe liues by vſing of her owne.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:5"/>
            <l>Her ſhop, her ware, her fame, her ſhame, her game,</l>
            <l>'Tis all her owne, which none from her can claime.</l>
            <l>And if ſhe be halfe mad, and Curſe and ſweare,</l>
            <l>And fight, and bite, and ſcratch, and domineere:</l>
            <l>Yet ſtill ſhe proues her patience to be ſuch,</l>
            <l>'Midſt all theſe paſſions ſhe will beare too much.</l>
            <l>She is not Couetous for any thing,</l>
            <l>For what ſhe hath, men doe vnto her bring,</l>
            <l>(Her Temp'rance is a vertue of much honour)</l>
            <l>And all her Commings in, are put vpon her.</l>
            <l>She's generall, ſhe's free, ſhe's liberall</l>
            <l>Of hand and purſe, ſhe's open vnto all,</l>
            <l>Shee is no miſerable hidebound wretch,</l>
            <l>To pleaſe her friend at any time ſhee'le ſtretch,</l>
            <l>At once ſhe can ſpeake <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>lye,</hi> or either,</l>
            <l>And is at home, abroad, and altogether.</l>
            <l>She's nimbler then a Tumbler, as I thinke</l>
            <l>Layes downe, and takes vp, whilſt a man can winke.</l>
            <l>And though ſhe ſeeme vnmeaſur'd in her pleaſure,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>'Tis otherwayes,</hi> a <hi>Yard</hi>'s her onely meaſure.</l>
            <l>But as moſt <hi>Whores</hi> are vicious in their fames,</l>
            <l>So many of them haue moſt Vertuous names,</l>
            <l>Though bad they be, they will not bate an Ace</l>
            <l>To be cald <hi>Prudence, Temp'rance, Faith,</hi> or <hi>Grace,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or <hi>Mercy, Charity,</hi> or many more,</l>
            <l>Good names (too good to giue to any <hi>Whore</hi>)</l>
            <l>Much from the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> they doe not ſwerue,</l>
            <l>For they haue Names which they doe ill deſerue,</l>
            <l>Onely betwixt them heere's the difference on't,</l>
            <l>A <hi>Whore</hi> receiues her Name firſt at the <hi>Font.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:6"/>
            <l>The Roman Biſhop takes a larger ſcope,</l>
            <l>For he doth Change his name, when hee's a Pope.</l>
            <l>As, if he were a Perſecuting <hi>Saul,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If he pleaſe hee'l be call'd a Preaching <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Is his name <hi>Swineſnowt,</hi> he can change the Caſe,</l>
            <l>And ſwap away that Name for <hi>Boniface.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If he be moſt vngodly, and enuious,</l>
            <l>Yet if he pleaſe, he will be called <hi>Pious.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Be he by Nature to all miſchiefe bent,</l>
            <l>He may and will be called <hi>Innocent,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And be he ne're ſo doggedly inclinde,</l>
            <l>Hee'le be nam'd <hi>Vrbane,</hi> if it be his minde.</l>
            <l>If he be much more fearefull then a Sheepe,</l>
            <l>The Name of <hi>Lee</hi> he may haue and keepe.</l>
            <l>And though he be vnmercifull yet ſtill,</l>
            <l>He may be called <hi>Clement</hi> if he will.</l>
            <l>Thus <hi>Popes</hi> may haue good names, though bad they bet</l>
            <l>And ſo may <hi>Whores</hi> though different in degree.</l>
            <l>The Annagram of WHORE'S her mortall foe,</l>
            <l>Deuided into two wordes, 'tis HER WO.</l>
            <l>And ſeriouſly (to lay all Ieſting by)</l>
            <l>A <hi>Whore</hi> is <hi>Her</hi> owne <hi>Wo,</hi> and miſery.</l>
            <l>For though ſhe haue all pleaſures at the full,</l>
            <l>Much more then <hi>Thaies,</hi> that proud <hi>Corinthian</hi> Trull</l>
            <l>Who ſuffered none but Kings and Potentates</l>
            <l>To haue their pleaſures, at Exceſſiue rates,</l>
            <l>Yet all that Deare bought Lechery would be</l>
            <l>The greater brand of laſting Infamy,</l>
            <l>And though her Carrion Corps, rich clad, high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d,</l>
            <l>(Halfe rotten liuing, and all rotten Dead)</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:6"/>
            <l>Who with her helliſh Courage, ſtout and hot,</l>
            <l>Abid the brunt of many a prickſhaft ſhot,</l>
            <l>Yet being dead, and doth Conſumed lye,</l>
            <l>Her euerlaſting ſhame ſhall neuer dye:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ixion</hi> (in his armes) he did ſuppoſe</l>
            <l>That he the Goddeſſe <hi>Iuno</hi> did incloſe:</l>
            <l>But in the end his franticke error ſhow'd,</l>
            <l>That all which he Embrac'd was but a Cloud.</l>
            <l>So whoſoeuer doe their <hi>Luſt</hi> embrace,</l>
            <l>In ſtead of <hi>Loue</hi> are clouded with diſgrace.</l>
            <l>The Godleſſe Goddeſſe <hi>Venus,</hi> honour'd farre,</l>
            <l>For Conqu'ring of the Conqu'ring God of Warre,</l>
            <l>To hide their ſhame they no defence could get,</l>
            <l>When limping <hi>Vulcan</hi> tooke them in a net,</l>
            <l>And being paſt ſhame, with that foule offence,</l>
            <l>Shee arm'd herſelfe with ſhameleſſe Impudence,</l>
            <l>And with vngodly articles would proue,</l>
            <l>That foule Concupiſcence and Luſt is Loue.</l>
            <l>For which each baudy Knaue, and filthy <hi>Whore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heere I haue for ſome 60. lines follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neius Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> in his <hi>Vanity of ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caces.</hi>
               </note>
            </l>
            <l>Her deuilliſh Diety doe ſtill adore.</l>
            <l>I haue read Hiſtories that doth Repeat</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Whores</hi> were of olde in eſtimation Great,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pandemus</hi> King of <hi>Corinth,</hi> he Erected</l>
            <l>(That he from <hi>Perſes</hi> power might be protected)</l>
            <l>A Temple vnto <hi>Venus,</hi> as ſome ſay,</l>
            <l>Where <hi>Whares</hi> might for his ſafety ſafely pray.</l>
            <l>And ſome in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> did Temples reare,</l>
            <l>In whom the <hi>Paphean</hi> Queene adored were,</l>
            <l>Where they that were the wickedſt <hi>Whores</hi> of all,</l>
            <l>Were the chiefe Prieſts in robes Pontificall.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:7"/>
            <l>And in the Ile of <hi>Paphes,</hi> 'twas the vſe</l>
            <l>Maydes got their Dowries, by their Corps abuſe,</l>
            <l>But if that order were allowed heere,</l>
            <l>So many would not Portions want I feare.</l>
            <l>The Art of Bawd'ry was in ſuch reſpect</l>
            <l>Amongſt th'<hi>Egiptians,</hi> that they did erect</l>
            <l>An Altar to <hi>Priapus,</hi> and their guiſe</l>
            <l>VVas, that their Prieſts on it did Sacrifice.</l>
            <l>VViſe <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> was in wit ſo poore,</l>
            <l>He Sacrific'd to <hi>Hermia,</hi> his <hi>whore.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Great <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> was ſo free and Common,</l>
            <l>And cald a Husband vnto euery woman.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Procullus</hi> Emperour, (the Story ſayes)</l>
            <l>Deſlowr'd one hundred Maydes<note n="*" place="margin">Sarmatian <hi>Maydes.</hi>
               </note> in Fifteene dayes.</l>
            <l>If all be true that Poets vſe to write,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hercules</hi> lay with Fifty in one night.</l>
            <l>When <hi>Heliogabilus,</hi> Romes Scepter ſway'd,</l>
            <l>And all the world his lawleſſe Lawes obay'd:</l>
            <l>He in his Court did cauſe a Stewes be made,</l>
            <l>Whereas <hi>Cum priuilegio, Whores</hi> did trade.</l>
            <l>H'inuited Two and twenty of his friends,</l>
            <l>And kindly to each one a <hi>Whore</hi> he lends.</l>
            <l>To ſet <hi>Whores</hi> free, that then in bondage lay,</l>
            <l>A mighty Maſſe of money he did pay,<note place="margin">30. pound waight a peece.</note>
            </l>
            <l>He (in one day) gaue to each <hi>whore</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A <hi>Duckat,</hi> (a large and ill beſtowed ſumme.)</l>
            <l>He made Orations vnto <hi>Whores,</hi> and ſaid</l>
            <l>They were his Soldiers, his Defence and ayde,</l>
            <l>And in his ſpeech he ſhew'd his wit s'acute,</l>
            <l>Of ſundry formes of Bawd'ry to diſpute.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:7"/>
            <l>And after giuing vnto euery <hi>Whore,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For liſt'ning to his tale three Duckats more,</l>
            <l>With Pardon vnto all, and Liberty</l>
            <l>That would be <hi>Whores</hi> within his Monarchy.</l>
            <l>And yearely penſions, he freely gaue,</l>
            <l>To keepe a Regiment of <hi>Whores,</hi> moſt braue.</l>
            <l>And oft he had (when hee in Progreſſe went)</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Whores,</hi> Bawdes, Pandeas, ſuch a Rabblement</l>
            <l>Sixe hundred Waggons, Hiſtory reports,</l>
            <l>Attended onely on theſe braue Conſorts.</l>
            <l>This was a Royall <hi>Whoremaſter</hi> indeed,</l>
            <l>A ſpeciall<note n="*" place="margin">Or rather malefaſtor</note> Benefactor at <hi>their</hi> need,</l>
            <l>But now ſince <hi>Heliogabilus</hi> deceaſt,</l>
            <l>I thinke the world with <hi>Whores</hi> is ſo increaſt,</l>
            <l>That if it had an Emperour as mad,</l>
            <l>He might haue twice ſo many as he had.</l>
            <l>For by experience we ſee euery day</l>
            <l>That bad thinges doe increaſe, good things decay.</l>
            <l>And vertue (with much care) from vertue breeds,</l>
            <l>Vice freely ſprings from vice like ſtincking weeds.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> King of <hi>Babilon,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Was to his <hi>whores</hi> ſuch a Companion,</l>
            <l>That he in their Attire did Sowe and ſing,</l>
            <l>(An exerciſe vnfitting for a King)</l>
            <l>This feruent Luſt, (which ſome call ardent Ioue)</l>
            <l>Did cauſe the Baſtard<note n="*" place="margin">Hercuier.</note> of the mighty <hi>Ioue</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To pleaſe his <hi>Iole,</hi> he tooke a Wheele</l>
            <l>And (laying by his Club) did Spin and Reele.</l>
            <l>Great <hi>loue</hi> himſelfe, could not this ſnare eſcape,</l>
            <l>Luſt led him on to many a ſhameleſſe Rape.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:8"/>
            <l>Poore <hi>Hebe, Hele,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> transformd himſelfe to all theſe ſhapes to attaine his deſrie.</note> 
               <hi>Danue,</hi> and <hi>Europa,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Alemena, Io, Semele,</hi> and <hi>Leada,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Antiopa, Aſterie, Ganimede,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Theſe and a number more his fancy fed.</l>
            <l>To compaſſe which his ſhifts were manifold</l>
            <l>T'a <hi>Bull,</hi> a Ram, a Swan, a ſhowre of Golde,</l>
            <l>To dreadfull Thunder, and conſuming Fire,</l>
            <l>And all to quench his inward flames deſire.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Apollo</hi> turn'd faire <hi>Daph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> into<note n="*" place="margin">The Bay tree or Lawrell.</note> 
               <hi>Bay,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Becauſe ſhe from his Luſt did flye away.</l>
            <l>He lou'd his <hi>Hiacinct,</hi> and his <hi>Coronis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As feruently as <hi>Venus</hi> lou'd <hi>Adonis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>So much he from his Godhead did de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne,</l>
            <l>That for a Wench he kept <hi>Adme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> Kine.</l>
            <l>And many other <hi>Gods</hi> haue gone aftray,</l>
            <l>If all be true which <hi>Ouids</hi> Booke doth ſay.</l>
            <l>Thus to fulfill their Luſts, and win their Truls,</l>
            <l>We ſee that theſe vngodly Gods were Guls.</l>
            <l>The mighty Captaine<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Achilles,</hi> who was flaine (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fotted to his Death) for the loue of <hi>Polixena.</hi>
               </note> of the <hi>Mermidous</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Being Captiu'd to theſe baſe paſſions,</l>
            <l>Met an vntimely vnexpected ſlaughter</l>
            <l>For faire <hi>Polixena,</hi> King <hi>Priams</hi> Daughter.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Lucretia's</hi> Rape, was <hi>Tarquins</hi> ouerthrowe,</l>
            <l>(Shame often payes the debt that ſinne doth owe)</l>
            <l>VVhot <hi>Philomela</hi> loſt, and <hi>Tereus</hi> wonne</l>
            <l>It cauſde the luſtfull Father<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tereus</hi> K. of <hi>Thrace,</hi> care of his own Son <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis</hi> made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to py-meat by his wife <hi>Frogne.</hi>
               </note> eate his Sonne.</l>
            <l>In this vice <hi>Nero</hi> tooke ſuch beaſtly ioy,</l>
            <l>He married was to <hi>Sporus,</hi> a young Boy,</l>
            <l>And <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riander,</hi>
               <note place="margin">* A Tyrant Prince in <hi>Corinth.</hi>
               </note> was with Luſt ſo led,</l>
            <l>He with <hi>Melliſſa</hi> lay, when ſhe was Dead.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:8"/>
            <l>
               <hi>Pigmalion,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Plutarte.</note> with an Image made of Stone,</l>
            <l>Did Loue and lodge; (I'le rather lye alone.)</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ariſtophanes,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Appius</hi> murthered himſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginias</hi> father had ſlaine her, to free her fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Luſt.</note> joyn'd in Loue would be</l>
            <l>To a ſhee Aſſe, but what an Aſſe was he.</l>
            <l>A Roman <hi>Appius</hi> did in Iayle abide</l>
            <l>For Loue of faire <hi>Virginia,</hi> where he dyde.</l>
            <l>Our ſecond <hi>Henry,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">K <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. King of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> Aged, Childiſh, fond,</l>
            <l>On the faire feature of faire <hi>Roſamond:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That it rais'd moſt vnnaturall hatefull ſtrife</l>
            <l>Betwixt himſelfe, his Children,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>At</hi> Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke.</note> and his wife.</l>
            <l>The end of which was, that the jealious Queene</l>
            <l>Did poyſon<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Shore.</note> 
               <hi>Roſamond</hi> in furious ſpleene.</l>
            <l>The fourth King <hi>Edward</hi> lower did diſcend.</l>
            <l>He to a Goldſmiths wife<note n="*" place="margin">She was <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whoſe Rape was accurſedly reuenged by hir bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> &amp; <hi>Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Geneſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> his loue did bend.</l>
            <l>This ſugred ſinne hath bin ſo generall,</l>
            <l>That it hath made the ſtrongeſt Champions fall.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em</hi> rauiſht<note n="*" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Dina,</hi> for which deed,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> number of the <hi>Sichemites</hi> did bleed,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Sampſon,</hi> in the prime of manly ſtrength</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Dallila,</hi> was ouercome at length</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng<note n="*" place="margin">2.<hi>Sam.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> frayly fell, and felt the paine,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d with much ſorrow, was reſtor'd againe,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ough <hi>Saul</hi> his foe he no way would offend,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this ſinne made him kill his loyall friend.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>much</hi> with <hi>Thamar,</hi> Inceſt did commit,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Abſolon</hi> depriu'd his Life for it.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> allow'd moſt Royall meanes,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> keepe 3. hundred Queenes, 7. hundred Queanes,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whoſe meanes to Idolaty he fell</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt as lowe as to the Gates of Hell.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:9"/>
            <l>At laſt repeating, he makes declaration,</l>
            <l>That all was vanity, and ſpirits vexation.</l>
            <l>Aboundance of Examples men may finde,</l>
            <l>Of Kings and Princes to this vice inclin'd,</l>
            <l>Which is no way for meaner men to goe,</l>
            <l>Becauſe their betters oft haue wandred ſo,</l>
            <l>For they were plagu'd of God, and ſo ſhall wee</l>
            <l>Much more, if of their ſinne we partners bee.</l>
            <l>To ſhew what Women haue bin plunged in</l>
            <l>The bottomleſſe Abiſſe of this ſweet ſinne:</l>
            <l>There are example of them infinite,</l>
            <l>Which I ne're meane to reade, much leſſe to write.</l>
            <l>To pleaſe the Reader though I'le ſet downe ſome,</l>
            <l>As they vnto my memory doe come.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Flora</hi> a <hi>Whore</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> great wealth did win,</l>
            <l>By her deare trading and her Commings in,</l>
            <l>Which wealth ſhe freely gaue when ſhe did dye</l>
            <l>Vnto the <hi>Roman</hi> people generally,</l>
            <l>For which they all (to ſhew their thankes vnto h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Made her a Goddeſſe, and did Reuerence doe her</l>
            <l>And <hi>Laies</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> ask'd <hi>Demoſthenes</hi>
            </l>
            <l>One hundred Crownes for one nights buſines,</l>
            <l>For which a crew of <hi>Whores</hi> did ſet vpon her,</l>
            <l>A <hi>Whore</hi> ſhe was, and <hi>Whores</hi> to death did ſtone</l>
            <l>There was a famous Whore<note n="*" place="margin">Shee was ſeruant to <hi>Exanthus,</hi> &amp; fellow to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſope</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buliſt.</note> 
               <hi>Rhodope</hi> nam'd</l>
            <l>Who for her gaine, at ſuch high price ſhe gam'd,</l>
            <l>That ſhe (moſt liberall) did the Charges beare,</l>
            <l>A ſtately high Piramides to Reare.</l>
            <l>Great <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> was much ouerſeene</l>
            <l>With <hi>Cleopatra</hi> the Aegiptian Queene:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:9"/>
            <l>And after ſhe inſnar'd <hi>Marke Anthony,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For which they both by their owne hands did dye.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Semiramis</hi> plaid the inhumane Trull,</l>
            <l>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Queene of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſlaine by her ſonne, whom ſhe would haue had to haue layne with her.</note> And was enamour'd with a beaſtly <hi>Bull:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>So did<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paſipha,</hi> wife to <hi>Minos</hi> king of <hi>Creete.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paſipha,</hi> but me thinkes 'tis ſtrange,</l>
            <l>That Queenes ſo far from womenhood ſhould range.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mirha</hi> (<hi>Adonis</hi> mother) caus'd her father</l>
            <l>The flow'r of her virginity to gather.</l>
            <l>If wiſe <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> had not well beene arm'd,</l>
            <l>Inchanting <hi>Circes,</hi> had his honour charm'd,</l>
            <l>When luſtfull <hi>Paris</hi> ſtole the luſtfull Punke</l>
            <l>Faire <hi>Hellen,</hi> had the Ship that bore them ſunke,</l>
            <l>Then thirty Kings in peace at home had ſtaide,</l>
            <l>Nor <hi>Troy</hi> or <hi>Troians</hi> in their ruines laide,</l>
            <l>Faire <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> a moſt royall <hi>Whore,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>(Wife vnto <hi>Claudins</hi> the Emperour)</l>
            <l>The ſports of <hi>Venus</hi> in the Stewes did play,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Meſſalina</hi> and <hi>Fauſtins</hi> two Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Sometimes full fiue and twenty times a day.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> did faire <hi>Fauſtine</hi> wed,</l>
            <l>And ſhe with Whoring did ad-horne his head.</l>
            <l>And many Princes and great Potentates,</l>
            <l>With <hi>Vulcans</hi> creſt haue arm'd their noble pates:</l>
            <l>This to the pooreſt Cuckold ſeemes a bliſs,</l>
            <l>That he with mighty Monarchs ſharer is,</l>
            <l>That though to be Cornuted be a griefe,</l>
            <l>Yet to haue ſuch braue partners, is reliefe.</l>
            <l>Theſe <hi>Whores</hi> &amp; <hi>Whoremaiſters,</hi> which I haue nam'd,</l>
            <l>And thouſands more (in Hiſtories defam'd)</l>
            <l>With partiall ſelfe-opinion did approue,</l>
            <l>Their ſenſuality and luſt was <hi>Loue.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:10"/>
            <l>When as the ods is more then day from night,</l>
            <l>Or fire from water, blacke from pureſt white.</l>
            <l>The one with <hi>God,</hi> one with the <hi>Deuill</hi> doth dwell,</l>
            <l>Loue comes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>heauen,</hi> and luſt doth ſpring fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>hell.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But the old Prouerb, ne're will be forgot,</l>
            <l>A Leachers loue is (like <hi>Sir Reuerence</hi>) hot.</l>
            <l>And on the ſuddaine cold as any ſtone,</l>
            <l>For when the luſt is paſt, the loue is gone.</l>
            <l>But loue is ſuch a bleſſing from on hie,</l>
            <l>Whoſe zealous feruency can neuer dye,</l>
            <l>It out-liues life, and the aſcending flame</l>
            <l>Mounis to the God of <hi>Loue,</hi> from whence it came.</l>
            <l>Luſt made<note n="*" place="margin">Geneſis.</note> 
               <hi>Seths</hi> ſonnes, with fornication vaine,</l>
            <l>Ioyne with the daughters of accurſed <hi>Caine.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And the world ſuff'red, for their fornication</l>
            <l>Depopulation, by the inundation.</l>
            <l>And twenty and foure thouſand <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Dyde for this ſinne amongſt the<note n="a" place="margin">Numbers.</note> 
               <hi>Midianites.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For the not puniſhing this fact (almoſt)</l>
            <l>The Tribe of<note n="b" place="margin">Iudge. 19.20. and 21. cha. 65000. were ſlaine of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, prod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained of the Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites only 600.</note> 
               <hi>Beniami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> were ſlaine and loſt.</l>
            <l>May this be call'd loue, then call vertue vice,</l>
            <l>And euery bawdy houſe, a Paradice.</l>
            <l>If luſt were loue, it would not like a Wolfe,</l>
            <l>Drowne Louers hearts in Deſperations Gulfe,</l>
            <l>A Theban,<note n="c" place="margin">For <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena</hi> the daughter of <hi>Oedi us</hi> and <hi>Iecaſla.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hemon,</hi> himſelfe madly kill'd,</l>
            <l>On his to deere deeres Tombe his heart blood ſpild</l>
            <l>For <hi>Pham</hi> (a poore Watermans ſweet ſake)</l>
            <l>Faire <hi>Saphe</hi> from a rocke, her<note n="d" place="margin">The more foole ſhee, though ſhe were a Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</note> neck ſhe brake.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pheadra,</hi> for her <hi>Hippollitus,</hi> they ſay,</l>
            <l>Did hang her ſelfe, and make a Holy-day.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:10"/>
            <l>And<note n="e" place="margin">Shee was daughter to <hi>Lycurgus</hi> K. of <hi>Thrace.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Phillis</hi> for<note n="f" place="margin">Sonne to <hi>Theſeus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Demophoon</hi> did as much,</l>
            <l>I'le neuer loue, if Loues effects be ſuch.</l>
            <l>To quench the <hi>Carthaginian</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>co.</hi> for <hi>Eneac,</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her ſelfe.</note> Queenes deſire,</l>
            <l>She burnt her ſelfe vpon a pile of fire;</l>
            <l>If either <hi>Piramus,</hi> or <hi>Thisby</hi> had</l>
            <l>Not beene ſtarke fooles, or elſe exceeding mad,</l>
            <l>The doting, idle miſconceiuing Elues,</l>
            <l>So deſperately, had ne're fore-done themſelues.</l>
            <l>Thus all the difference betwixt loue and luſt,</l>
            <l>Is, one is iuſt, the other is vniuſt,</l>
            <l>Search but in Hiſtories, and men may finde</l>
            <l>Examples beyond numb'ring, of this kinde,</l>
            <l>How of both Sexes, each eſtate, and ſort</l>
            <l>Of people; from the Cottage to the Court,</l>
            <l>Haue madly ran this courſe ſom hang'd, ſom drownd,</l>
            <l>Burnt, ſtaru'd, &amp; ſtabd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with many a wound,</l>
            <l>Or pin'd away like Coxcombs, euer crauing</l>
            <l>To haue the thing, that's neuer worth the hauing.</l>
            <l>In <hi>Antwerp,</hi> many filthy <hi>Whores</hi> I ſaw,</l>
            <l>That for their Trading were allowde by Law.</l>
            <l>And I in <hi>Prague</hi> did ſee a ſtreete of <hi>Whores,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>An Engliſh mile in length, who at their dores,</l>
            <l>Did ſtand and ply (rich clad, and painted rare)</l>
            <l>More hard then euer I plyde for a fare.</l>
            <l>Th' <hi>Italian</hi> Stewes (to make the Pope good cheere)</l>
            <l>Payd twenty thouſand Duckets in a<note n="h" place="margin">Almoſt euery yere, a ducket is more then, 8. ſhillings, which ſum is 8000. l.</note> yeeee.</l>
            <l>Beſides, they giue a Prieſt (t'amend his fee)</l>
            <l>The profit of a <hi>Whore,</hi> or two or three,</l>
            <l>Me thinkes it muſt be bad Diuinity,</l>
            <l>That with the Stewes hath ſuch affinity,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:11"/>
            <l>'Tis a mad doctrine Leachery ſhall pay</l>
            <l>A Church-mans ſtipend, that ſhould preach &amp; pray</l>
            <l>And in thoſe Stewes, where women are ſo common</l>
            <l>In entertaining all, refuſing no man,</l>
            <l>Whereas a father with a <hi>Whore</hi> may lye,</l>
            <l>Which done, his ſonne his place may hap ſupply,</l>
            <l>And then an Vnckle, or a brother may</l>
            <l>Succeed each other in that damned play.</l>
            <l>For no propinquity, or no degree</l>
            <l>Of Kin, that haunt there, that can ſweare th'are free</l>
            <l>From this commixion, and which is worſt,</l>
            <l>A <hi>Whore</hi> may haue a Baſtard, borne and nurſt,</l>
            <l>And growne a woman, and to this Trade ſet her,</l>
            <l>May be a <hi>Whore</hi> to him that did beget her.</l>
            <l>Or to her brothers, or to all her Kin,</l>
            <l>She may be proſtituted in this ſin.</l>
            <l>And therefore to conclude this point, I muſe</l>
            <l>That Chriſtian Common-wealthes allow a Stues;</l>
            <l>I thinke that Thieues as well allow'd ſhould be,</l>
            <l>As <hi>Whores</hi> and <hi>Whore maiſters</hi> ſhould thus be free.</l>
            <l>They from the heathen doe examples bring,</l>
            <l>That <hi>Whoring,</hi> is a rare commodious thing,</l>
            <l>There was an ancient vſe in <hi>Babylon,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When as a womans ſtock was ſpent and gone,</l>
            <l>Her liuing it was lawfull then to get,</l>
            <l>Her carkaſſe out to Liuerie to let.</l>
            <l>And <hi>Venus</hi> did allow the <hi>Cyprian</hi> Dames,</l>
            <l>To get their liuings by their bodies ſhames,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Lycurgus</hi> did a Law in <hi>Sparta</hi> make,</l>
            <l>That all men might their Barren wiues forſake:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:11"/>
            <l>And by the ſame Law it ordained was,</l>
            <l>Wiues might vnable husbands turne to grals.</l>
            <l>And the wiſe <hi>Solon</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Allow'd <hi>Whores</hi> to be free for any man.</l>
            <l>And though theſe things the Pagan people did,</l>
            <l>Yet Chriſtian gouernments theſe things forbid,</l>
            <l>But there's no Common-wealth maintaines the ſame,</l>
            <l>But where the<note n="a" place="margin">Not in any place but where Romes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy is allowed.</note> Pope is Landlord of the game.</l>
            <l>The Stewes in <hi>England</hi> bore a beaſtly ſway,</l>
            <l>Till the eight<note n="b" place="margin">Anno Regni <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> baniſh'd them away,</l>
            <l>And ſince thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon <hi>whores</hi> were quite put down,</l>
            <l>A damned crew of priuate <hi>whores</hi> are growne,</l>
            <l>So that the deuill will be doing ſtill,</l>
            <l>Either with publique or with priuate ill.</l>
            <l>Thus much for <hi>whoring</hi> I muſt ſay agen,</l>
            <l>It hath produced many valiant men:</l>
            <l>Braue Baſtards, haue beene famous Conquerours,</l>
            <l>And ſome great Lords, and Kings, and Emperours.</l>
            <l>As <hi>Hereules Ioues</hi> mighty Baſtard ſonne,</l>
            <l>And<note n="c" place="margin">So ſayes <hi>Cornelius Agrippa,</hi> but I finde it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in Quintus Curtius.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> King of <hi>Macedon:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Clodouee</hi> King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> from Baſtardy,</l>
            <l>And <hi>William</hi> Conquerour, from <hi>Normandy,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Theſe and a number more I could recite,</l>
            <l>Beſides the vnknowne number's infinite.</l>
            <l>And ſure that wretched man that married is</l>
            <l>Vnto a wife diſpos'd to this amiſs,</l>
            <l>Is mad to wrong himſelfe at all thereby,</l>
            <l>With heart griefe and tormenting iealouſie.</l>
            <l>If he hath cauſe for't, let him then forſake her,</l>
            <l>And pray God mend her, or the deuill take her:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:12"/>
            <l>If he hath no cauſe to be iealous then,</l>
            <l>He's worthy to be made the ſcorne of men,</l>
            <l>Thus cauſe or no cauſe, man himſelfe ſhould arme,</l>
            <l>That iealouſie ſhould neuer doe him harme.</l>
            <l>The <hi>Nicholaitanes,</hi> to auoyd the paine</l>
            <l>Of iealouſie, amongſt them did ordaine,</l>
            <l>That all their married wiues, of each degree,</l>
            <l>To euery one a common <hi>Whore</hi> ſhould be.</l>
            <l>And ſo amongſt them one could hardly finde,</l>
            <l>A Cuckold that did beare a iealous minde.</l>
            <l>When I but thinke what Sciences, and Arts,</l>
            <l>What men and women, full of ex'lent parts,</l>
            <l>Forget their functions, lay their vertues by,</l>
            <l>And waite and liue, and thriue by Leacherie.</l>
            <l>A Poets Art, all other Arts excell,</l>
            <l>If he hath skill and grace to vſe it well:</l>
            <l>Yet many times 'tis vs'd moſt baſe and vile,</l>
            <l>When it deſcends vnto a bawdy ſtile,</l>
            <l>To turne good humane ſtudies, and diuine,</l>
            <l>Into moſt beaſtly lines, like <hi>Aretine;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To ſeeke to merrit euer-liuing Bayes,</l>
            <l>For ſordid ſtuffe (like <hi>Ouids</hi> luſtfull Layes.)</l>
            <l>With falſe bewitching verſes to entice</l>
            <l>Fraile creatures from faire vertue to foule vice,</l>
            <l>Whoſe flatt'ry makes a <hi>whore</hi> to ſeeme a Saint,</l>
            <l>That ſtinkes like carrion, with her pox and paint.</l>
            <l>Comparing her (with falſe and odious lies)</l>
            <l>To all that's in or vnderneath the skies.</l>
            <l>Her eyes to <hi>Sunnes,</hi> that doth the <hi>Sunne</hi> Ecclips,</l>
            <l>Her cheekes are Roſes, (Rubies are her lips)</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:12"/>
            <l>Her white and red Carnation mixt with ſnow,</l>
            <l>Her teeth to orientall pearle, a Rowe,</l>
            <l>Her voyce like Muſick of the heau'nly Spheares,</l>
            <l>Her haire like thrice refined golden Wires,</l>
            <l>Her breath more ſweet then Arromatick drugs,</l>
            <l>Like Mownts of Allablaſter are her drugs,</l>
            <l>Her <hi>Bracilets, Rings,</hi> her <hi>Scarfe</hi> her <hi>Fan,</hi> her <hi>Chaine,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Are ſubiects to inſpire a Poets braine:</l>
            <l>But aboue all her <hi>Smock</hi> moſt praiſe doth win,</l>
            <l>For 'tis the Curtaine next vnto her skin,</l>
            <l>Her looſe <hi>Gowne,</hi> for her looſer body fit,</l>
            <l>Shall be adored with a flaſh of wit,</l>
            <l>And from the <hi>Chin-clowt,</hi> to the lowly <hi>Slipper,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>Helliconian</hi> ſtreames his praiſe ſhall dipher.</l>
            <l>I leaue vnnam'd what is affected beſt,</l>
            <l>As 'tis moſt fit, for it maintaines the reſt,</l>
            <l>Her thighes, her knees, her legs, her feete, and all,</l>
            <l>From top to toe are ſupernaturall.</l>
            <l>Her Iuory hands, with ſaphire veines inlayde,</l>
            <l>VVhich cannot be by mortall Pen diſplayde.</l>
            <l>Her ſmile makes cold December Sommer like,</l>
            <l>Her frowne, hot Iune with ſhiuering Froſt can ſtrike,</l>
            <l>And life and death doth in her lookes abide,</l>
            <l>Or many Knaues and Fooles that ſaid ſo lyde.</l>
            <l>Her Shapperoones, her Perriwigs and Tires,</l>
            <l>Are Reliques, which this flatt'ry much admires,</l>
            <l>Rebatoes, Maske, her Busk and Busk-point to,</l>
            <l>Are things to which mad men muſt homage doe.</l>
            <l>Her Verdingale, her Garters, Shooes and Roſes,</l>
            <l>Her Girdle that her waſtfull waſte incloſes.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:13"/>
            <l>Not one of theſe but's honour'd with a Sonnet,</l>
            <l>If the ſaid Poet be but ſet vpon it.</l>
            <l>Another ſeekes to winne his Wenches will,</l>
            <l>With oyly Oratories ſmooting skill:</l>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="oratory">
                        <head>As thus.</head>
                        <p>MOſt ineſtimable Magazin of Beauty, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Maiſter-piece of Nature, Perfections won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Loues Quinteſſence, in whom the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> and maieſtie of <hi>Iuno,</hi> the feature of <hi>Cithere</hi> the wiſedome of <hi>Ioues</hi> Braine-bred<note n="*" place="margin">Pallas.</note> 
                           <hi>Girle,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> chaſtity of <hi>Diana,</hi> and the conſtancie of <hi>Luc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> haue their domeſticall habitation, who w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the <hi>Goddeſſes</hi> are deifide, with the <hi>Graces</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, with the <hi>Vertues</hi> ſtellifide, with the Muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> honourd, and with the ſenſes admired: vouchſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> dread Empreſſe of my Affections, to pardon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> intruſiue boldneſſe of my vntun'd tongue (which was neuer tipt with the Courtly Gloſſe of Adula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) who being the Ambaſſadour of my heart doth proſtrate my ſelfe and my beſt ſeruices to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> diſpoſed of at your great commaunds, and as the Refulgent beames of <hi>Titan</hi> makes purity of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſo one glance or glimpſe of the tranflucen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of your eyes ſunne dazeling corruſcancie, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> exile all the clowdy vapours of heart-tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting moody mellancholly, that like an vſurpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb facs="tcp:177518:13"/>Tyrant hath Captiuated your humble ſuppliant, thus feruently to Implore your Clemency.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <l>Heere's a ſweete deale of ſcimble ſcamble ſtuffe,</l>
            <l>To pleaſe my Lady <hi>Wagtayle,</hi> (marry muffe)</l>
            <l>Gep with the <hi>Grinkcomes,</hi> (but I ſpeake too late)</l>
            <l>This kinde of flatt'ry, makes a <hi>Whore</hi> take ſtate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Crinkcomes</hi> is an Vtopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an worde, which is in Engliſh a <hi>P.</hi> at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note>
            </l>
            <l>Growes pocky proud, &amp; in ſuch port doth beare her,</l>
            <l>That ſuch poore ſcabs as I, muſt not come neare her.</l>
            <l>Thus may ſhe liue, (much honour'd for her Crimes)</l>
            <l>And haue the Poxe ſome twelue or 13. times,</l>
            <l>And ſhee may be ſo bountifull agen,</l>
            <l>To ſell thoſe Poxe to three or foureſcore men.</l>
            <l>And thus the Surgeons may get more by farre</l>
            <l>By <hi>Whores</hi> and Peace, then by the Sword and warre.</l>
            <l>And thus a <hi>Whore</hi> (if men conſider of it)</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an encreaſing gainefull peece of profit.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of all <hi>Whores,</hi> that I haue nam'd before,</l>
            <l>There's none ſo Cunning as the Citty <hi>Whore,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee hath ſo many ſeuerall ſorts of Bawdes,</l>
            <l>To cloake and couer her deceipts and fraudes,</l>
            <l>That ſure the Deuill cannot more deuiſe</l>
            <l>Then ſhe, to blinde her horned Husbands eyes.</l>
            <l>The offers Purles to ſell, and fine Bone-lace,</l>
            <l>And whiſpers that her Friend's in ſuch a place:</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecond offers Starch, and tels her how</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſweet-heart tarries for her at the Plowe,</l>
            <l>A third ſels Wafers, and a fourth hath Pins,</l>
            <l>And with theſe tricks theſe Bawdes admittance wins.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:14"/>
            <l>That had her Husband <hi>Argos</hi> eyes, yet he</l>
            <l>By theſe deceiuers ſhould deceiued be,</l>
            <l>If all theſe fayle, a Begger woman may,</l>
            <l>A ſweet Loue letter to her hands conuay.</l>
            <l>Or a neate Laundreſſe, or a Hearbwife can,</l>
            <l>Carry a ſleeueleſſe meſſage now and than,</l>
            <l>Or if this fayle, her teeth may Ake (forſooth)</l>
            <l>And then the Barbar muſt come drawe a Tooth.</l>
            <l>Or elſe ſhe may be ſicke (vpon Condition)</l>
            <l>That ſuch a Doctor may be her Phyſition,</l>
            <l>He feeles her pulſes, and applies his trade</l>
            <l>With Potions which th' Apothecary made,</l>
            <l>All's one for that, her health ſhe quickly gaines,</l>
            <l>Her Husband payes the Doctor for his paines.</l>
            <l>But of all Bawdes, Golde is the Bawde indeed,</l>
            <l>It ſeldome ſpeakes but it is ſure to ſpeed:</l>
            <l>It can blinde Watches, open bolts and lockes,</l>
            <l>Breake walles of Stone, as hard as Marble rockes:</l>
            <l>Make Iron barres giue way, and Gates flye ope,</l>
            <l>Giues Luſt the reynes to run with boundleſſe ſee</l>
            <l>Kills Iealouſie, appeaſes Riuals, and</l>
            <l>Doth what the owners will or can Command,</l>
            <l>And laſt of all it ſtops the biting iawes</l>
            <l>Of the iuſt rigorous, and ſeuereſt Lawes.</l>
            <l>I therefore ſay, he that hath Golden pelfe,</l>
            <l>Hath a good Bawde, if ſo he pleaſe himſelfe,</l>
            <l>Thoſe that hath Gold, can want no Bawds or Que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Except they vſe a meane, to guide their meanes.</l>
            <l>To end this point, this conſequence Ile graunt,</l>
            <l>Thoſe that haue Golden Bawds, no <hi>Whores</hi> can w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:14"/>
            <l>And though the mighty power of <hi>Golde</hi> be ſuch,<note place="margin">A ſeraping miſerable father, that cares not how he get Golde to leaue it to a Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter his Son, is his Sons proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Bawd.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Yet <hi>Siluer</hi> (many times) can doe as much:</l>
            <l>Thus euery wealthy <hi>Whoremaſter</hi> may beare</l>
            <l>His <hi>Bawde</hi> in's purſe, or pocket any where.</l>
            <l>For mine owne part, I liue not in ſuch want,</l>
            <l>But that I eate and ſleepe, though Coyne be ſcant:</l>
            <l>And cauſe I want the <hi>Bawde</hi> I nam'd before,</l>
            <l>By Conſequence I needs muſt want the <hi>Whore.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And wanting of them both, I hope to be</l>
            <l>From <hi>Gowtes, Pox,</hi> and extortion euer free.</l>
            <l>But as there's wondrous difference in mens meate,</l>
            <l>So is the ods of <hi>Whores</hi> exceeding great:</l>
            <l>Some <hi>Rampant,</hi> &amp; ſome <hi>Couchant,</hi> and ſome <hi>Paſſant,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Some <hi>Guardant</hi> &amp; ſome <hi>Dormant,</hi> &amp; ſome <hi>Creſſant,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Some <hi>Pendant,</hi> ſome (a Pox on't) but the beſt on't,</l>
            <l>A priuate <hi>Whore,</hi> trades ſafely, there's the Ieſt on't.</l>
            <l>Beſides, as <hi>Whores</hi> are of a ſeuerall cut,</l>
            <l>So fitting Titles on them ſtill are put:</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or if a Princes loue to her decline,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or manners ſake ſhee's call'd a <hi>Concubine:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a great Lord, or Knight affect a <hi>Whore,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>She muſt be tearm'd his Honours <hi>Paramore,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The rich Gull Gallant call's her <hi>Deare</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ducke, Lambe, Squall, Sweethart, Cony,</hi> and his <hi>Doue:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pretty <hi>Wench</hi> ſhe's with the Countrey-man,</l>
            <l>And a <hi>Kinde Siſter</hi> with the Puritane,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e's a Prieſts <hi>Lemman,</hi> and a Tinkers <hi>Pad.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Dell,</hi> or <hi>Doxy</hi> (though the names be bad)</l>
            <l>And amongſt Soldiers this ſweet peece of Vice</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> counted for a Captaines <hi>Cockatrice.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:15"/>
            <l>But the mad Raſcall, when he's fiue parts drunke,</l>
            <l>Cals her his <hi>Drah,</hi> his <hi>Queane,</hi> his <hi>ſyll,</hi> or <hi>Punke:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And in his fury 'gins to Rayle and Rore,</l>
            <l>Then with full mouth, he truely cals her <hi>Whore,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And ſo I leaue her, to her hot deſires,</l>
            <l>'Mongſt <hi>Pimps</hi> and <hi>Panders,</hi> and baſe <hi>Apleſquire</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To mend or end, when Age or Pox will make her</l>
            <l>Deteſted, and <hi>Whoremaſters</hi> all forſake her.</l>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Compariſon betwixt a <hi>Whore</hi> and a <hi>Booke.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>ME thinkes I heare ſome Cauillers obiect</l>
               <l>That 'tis a Name abſurd and indirect,</l>
               <l>To giue a Booke the Title of a <hi>Whore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When ſure I thinke no Name befits it more.</l>
               <l>For like a <hi>Whore</hi> by day light, or by Candle,</l>
               <l>'Tis euer free for euery Knaue to handle:</l>
               <l>And as a new <hi>Whore</hi> is belou'd and ſought,</l>
               <l>So is a new <hi>Booke</hi> in requeſt and bought,</l>
               <l>VVhen <hi>Whores</hi> waxe old &amp; ſtale, they're out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Olde Pamphlets are moſt ſubiect to ſuch fate.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Whores</hi> haue Panders, to emblaze their worth,</l>
               <l>So theſe haue Stationers to ſet them forth.</l>
               <l>And as an olde <hi>Whore</hi> may be painted new</l>
               <l>VVith borrowed Beauty, faire vnto the view,</l>
               <l>VVhereby ſhe for a fine freſh <hi>whore</hi> may paſſe,</l>
               <l>Yet is ſhe but the Rotten <hi>whore</hi> ſhe was.</l>
               <l>So Stationers, their olde caſt Bookes can grace,</l>
               <l>And by new Titles paint a freſh their face,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177518:15"/>
               <l>VVhereby for Currant they are paſt away,</l>
               <l>As if they had come forth but yeſterday.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Booke</hi> is Dedicated, now and than</l>
               <l>To ſome great worthy, or vnworthy man:</l>
               <l>Yet for all that 'tis common vnto me,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thee, or he, or all eſtates that be,</l>
               <l>And ſo a man may haue a <hi>Whore</hi> (forſooth)</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppoſing ſhe is onely for his tooth,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t if the truth he would ſearch out and looke,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e's common vnto all men like a Booke.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Booke</hi> with gawdy Coate, and ſilken ſtringes,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe inſide's full of Obſceane beaſtly thinges,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like a <hi>Whore,</hi> Capariſon'd and trap'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull of Infection, to all miſchiefe apt.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>one <hi>Whore</hi> may be common vnto any,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one <hi>Booke,</hi> may be Dedicate to many.</l>
               <l>And ſure I ſay, and hope I ſpeake no ſlaunder,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a <hi>Booke,</hi> the <hi>Poet</hi> is the Pander.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> proſtitutes his Muſe to euery one,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich ſhould be Conſtant vnto one alone,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his is a kinde of Bawd'ry vile and baſe,</l>
               <l>Is bounty, and is Poetryes diſgrace.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d leaſt they ſhould be loſt it is ordain'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>Bookes</hi> within a Library are Chain'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee that to himſelfe will keepe a <hi>Whore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Chaine her, or ſhe'le trade with forty more.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Bookes</hi> are leafe by leafe oft turn'd and toſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are the Garments of a <hi>whore</hi> (almoſt)</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> both of them, with a wet finger may</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſolded or vnfolded, Night or Day.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177518:16"/>
               <l>Moreouer 'tis not very hard to proue,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Bookes</hi> and <hi>Whores</hi> may Riuals be in Loue,</l>
               <l>(To purchaſe mens diſpleaſures I am loth)</l>
               <l>But ſure good Schollers ſtill hath lou'd them both.</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Bookes</hi> haue their <hi>Errataes</hi> at the laſt</l>
               <l>That tels their Errors and offences paſt.</l>
               <l>So many great <hi>Whores</hi> did in ſtate ſuruiue,</l>
               <l>But when Death did their hatefull liues depriue,</l>
               <l>Their <hi>faults eſcap'd</hi> and their <hi>Errataes</hi> then</l>
               <l>Hath beene made manifeſt and knowne to men.</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Bookes</hi> and <hi>Whores</hi> to wicked purpoſe bent</l>
               <l>Doe, for their faults receiue one puniſhment.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Bookes</hi> are often burnt, and quite forgotten,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Whores</hi> are ouerſtew'd, or roſted rotten.</l>
               <l>Experience ſhewes that <hi>Bookes</hi> much knowledge bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And by experience <hi>Whores</hi> know <hi>many Thinges.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as true Iuſtice, all mens loſſe repaires,</l>
               <l>So <hi>whores</hi> doe giue to all men what is their's.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Terence</hi> ſhe learnes, yet will ſhe much Rebuke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>If we doe play the part of true <hi>Eunuchus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As <hi>Bookes</hi> prophane, or elſe Hereticall,</l>
               <l>Or ſcurrillous, non ſence Seiſmaticall,</l>
               <l>Peruerts mans Iudgement, and his ſoule pollutes,</l>
               <l>Such are all <hi>whores,</hi> and ſuch will be their Fruites</l>
               <l>Some Slouens ſoyle a <hi>Booke</hi> in little ſpace,</l>
               <l>And ſlauer it, and ſo the Leaues deface:</l>
               <l>And ſome againe will take a cleanly courſe</l>
               <l>To reade it dayly, yet 'tis ne're the worſe.</l>
               <l>So ſome men vſe a <hi>whore,</hi> when once they haue</l>
               <l>They'le touze and teare, and beaſtly all beſlauer</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177518:16"/>
               <l>When Forty neat <hi>whoremaſters</hi> might haue play'd</l>
               <l>And vſde her, and ſhe ſtill be thought a Mayde.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that doth Read a <hi>Booke</hi> he likes, would be</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>one, from any Interruption free,</l>
               <l>And he that with a <hi>whore,</hi> would toy or iye,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thinke deſires no other Company.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Bookes</hi> are wet, their beauty's gone or ſoyl'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, waſh a <hi>whore,</hi> and all her paintings ſpoyl'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d as an olde <hi>whore</hi> (ſpight of Paint or cloathing)</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lls at the laſt, the obiect of mens loathing,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om'd and vnpittyed, and to finiſh all,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es in a Ditch, or in an Hoſpitall.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pamphlets, and ſome workes of writers Graue</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vſde much worſe then <hi>whores</hi> by many a Knaue.</l>
               <l>Who ne're regards the matter or the price,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> teare like Tyrants, to wrap Drugs or Spice,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is worſe in Priuy matters vſe them.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worſt of all, like Roarers they abuſe them,</l>
               <l>When as they Rend good Bookes to light and dry</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acco</hi> (Englands bainefull Diety).</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 'tis a thing I ne're thought on before,<note n="*" place="margin">Now a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dayes.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Booke's</hi> examin'd ſtricter then a <hi>whore.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re's not a Sheet, a Leafe, a Page, a Vearſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orde, a ſillable, or letter (ſcarce)</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that (Authority) with Iudgements eye,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diligently looke, and ſearch, and pry,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gage the ſence, and firſt will vnderſtand all,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt in a Phraſe, or word, there lurke a ſcandall.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my poore <hi>whore</hi> in this hath not bin ſpar'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> skirts were curtayld, and her nayles were<note n="*" place="margin">She wold haue ſcrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched elſe.</note> par'd.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177518:17"/>
               <l>All's one for that, though ſhe ſuch vſage had,</l>
               <l>She's not left naked, though not richly clad,</l>
               <l>I knew ſhe muſt be queſtion'd and I ſay,</l>
               <l>I am right glad ſhe ſcap'd ſo well away.</l>
               <l>And ſhould all <hi>whores</hi> of high and lowe Degree,</l>
               <l>(As <hi>Bookes</hi> are) to account thus called be,</l>
               <l>The Whoriſh number would waxe very ſmall,</l>
               <l>Or elſe men neuer could examine all.</l>
               <l>This Booke my <hi>Whore</hi> or elſe this <hi>whore</hi> my Boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>(Shee beares both Names, ſo neither is miſtooke)</l>
               <l>Reſpects not all her enemies a ſtraw,</l>
               <l>If ſhe offended, ſhe hath had the Law,</l>
               <l>She was examin'd, and ſhe did Confeſſe,</l>
               <l>And hath endur'd the torture of the Preſſe:</l>
               <l>Her faults are Printed vnto all mens ſight,</l>
               <l>Vnpartially declar'd in blacke and white,</l>
               <l>And laſt, in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and in the ſtreet</l>
               <l>She ſuffers Pennance vp and downe in Sheets.</l>
               <l>And if all <hi>Whores,</hi> to doe the like were made,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Linnen Draper</hi> were the richeſt Trade.</l>
               <l>If any <hi>Whore</hi> be honeſter then mine is,</l>
               <l>Ile write no more but ſtop my mouth with</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177518:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
